hour hello everyone and welcome I'm Dr
Michael Greer coming to you live from my
treadmill for a very exciting webinar
one of my favorite things in the whole
wide world is to be proven wrong and boy
did this topic do it if you were like me
get ready for a 180 in your
thinking this was originally part of my
preserving your teeth chapter in my
upcoming book how not to age but had to
be cut due to space constraints the book
was supposed to be 600 pages but I wrote
over 2,000 pages with 13,000 plus
citations so I had to cut more than half
the book and so this floration section
got asked but you are all gonna get to
see it right here right now but first
some quick housekeeping Logistics as I
mentioned last two
times uh Zoom boom has changed your
default view so if when the videos are
playing and you want to maximize the
video there's a little gray vertical bar
between the video and the panelist you
can click and drag over or you can click
on the view in the upper right and
maximize the video don't want you to
miss anything if it ain't time you run
to technical difficulties there are live
chat Zoom staff standing by let me
uh uh let me put that in the chat
here okay okay I just put the URL in the
chat for everybody if you're unable if
they are unable to help we have
nutrition facts uh staff standing by too
and I will paste how to get a hold of
them in the chat as well please reserve
the Q&A button that you see in the zoom
window to ask content questions as
opposed to like you know technical
difficulty kind of things uh today's
webinar is only an hour um but I resered
some time for Q&A at the end so feel
free anytime any time any questions come
up to just type in you don't have to
wait till the end um and then uh the
nutrition facts team will compile um
some of the most kind of common uh uh
questions and I will answer them at the
end don't have to worry about taking
notes or anything after the webinar is
over not only going to send you a full
recording of it but also a free link to
download all the videos in high depth so
you can see the videos and all their
full resolution Glory the first video
today is water fluoridation effective in
other words does it work to reduce tooth
decay let's find
out all right let me just make sure I
got all my settings right now that I'm
coming back on board here I think this
should
work all
right let's do
this a meta analysis of all the studies
on the dental health implications of
vegetarian dies showed significantly
fewer decayed teeth missing teeth and
the number of teeth with fillings one of
the studies that bucked the trend and
showed that vegetarians had more
cavities blamed the excess Decay on the
fact that vegetarians were significantly
less likely to choose fluoride
containing toothpaste supported by the
fact that those who did use toothpaste
with fluoride had significantly fewer
decayed teeth than those who didn't
fluide is thought to protect teeth by
improving the intrinsic stability of the
mineral structural Dental enamel a
recent metaanalysis of nearly a 100
randomized control Trials of fluoride
toothpaste involving more than 10,000
people found High certainty evidence
that toothpaste containing the typical
amount of fluoride reduces tooth decay
significantly more than non-fluoride
toothpaste in both children and adults
but what about the addition of fluoride
to the water supply a medical consensus
of Public Health authorities around the
world has considered water fluoridation
at appropriate levels as a safe and
effective means to prevent cavities on a
CommunityWide scale in fact the CDC the
US Center for Disease Control and
prevention deemed fluoridation of
drinking water as one of the top 10
Public Health achievements of the 20th
century however Community water
fluoridation has long been a flasho of
pmic and polarization anti fluoridation
activists underscore that there's no
human dietary requirement for fluoride
and argue that water fluoridation isn't
effective enough to justify the costs
which may include health
risks first some background before I
dive into the controversy Floyd is a
mineral element in the Earth's crust
that naturally occurs in most Water
Supplies this is one of the reasons
fluoridation has withstood
constitutional challenges courts have
ruled that rather than an added
medication fluide can be seen as a
nutrient found naturally in some areas
but not others in fluoridation of Water
Supplies is a matter of just leveling
the playing field particularly for poor
communties who may have limited access
to Dental Care fluoridation can be
defined as the upward or downward
adjustment the level of fluoride content
in drinking water to an optimal level
just enough to prevent cavities but not
enough to cause fosis or or cosmetic
changes to the teeth it all started in
1901 with an investigation into Colorado
Brownstein grotesque brown stains on the
teeth of Colorado Springs residents at
the same time teeth afflicted by the
condition were surprisingly and
inexplicably resistant to Decay after
fluoride was identified as the basis for
these changes a nationwide survey of
fluoride levels and drinking water in
the 1930s led to the discovery that
fluoride could reach levels around one
part per million without causing serious
fosis uh hoping to get the best of both
worlds Grand Rapids Michigan in 1945
became the first city in the world to
fluoridate its water supply within 11
years cavity rates among children in
Grand Rapids was reportedly down more
than 60% and a floration movement was
born today about two dozen countries
fluoridate their drinking water dozens
of others have naturally fluoridated
water or instead add fluoride to milk or
table salt floration push back started
almost immediately in the United States
the obsession of doct strange Love's
Colonel Ripper with the purity of his
precious bodily fluids was based on re
life right-wing Red Scare conspiracy
theories that floration was meant to
produce moronic atheistic slaves who
would bow to the communist
today's social media is also Rife with
anti fluoridation messages Studies have
found that 63% of Instagram posts
regarding fluoride could be classified
as anti fluoride 64% of tweets on
Twitter 99% of YouTube videos and up to
100% of fluoride groups and Pages found
on Facebook were anti fluide years
before covid the anti fluoridation
Crusade was considered a case study of
digital pandemics of Public Health
misinformation in the year before Co the
first worldwide survey of the crisis of
confidence in science of 140,000 people
in 140 countries found that only 18% of
humanity appeared to have a high level
of trust in
science to my pleasant surprise though
despite so many institutional failures a
2020 followup of the study found trust
in science actually increased after
covid where does the science land on
water fluoridation first let me address
efficacy the CDC attributes the Steep
decline in dental decay in the United
States in the latter half of the 20th
century to water fluoridation but
similar declines were noted in non
fluoridated countries attributed in
large part to the widespread global
distribution of fluoride toothpaste the
best evidence we have comes from
prospective studies with concurrent
controls comparing cavity rates over
time in floridated versus non floridated
populations there have been more than a
hundred such studies to date and overall
florid results in 35% fewer decayed
missing or filled baby teeth and 26%
fewer decayed missing or filled
permanent teeth so Community
fluoridation does indeed help to cut
down on cavities the question then
becomes at what cost which we'll
discuss
next okay like everything in medicine
it's a matter of balancing the risks and
benefits talking about the benefits
water fluoridation really does seem to
cut down on cavities what are the risks
well start with a discussion of
something I briefly mentioned called
fluorosis this should do
it fluide research over a half century
historically established water
fluoridation to be safe when used at
typical fluoridation doses of one part
per million however naturally
fluoridated Waters up around two parts
per million can put children under the
age of nine at increased risk for dental
fosis and a lifetime of drinking water
at four parts per million can cause
skeletal fosis and increase the risk of
bone fractures you can see these kinds
of levels in the Earth's natural
fluoride belts that extend from Turkey
through Iraq Iran and Afghanistan China
and Japan the reason susceptibility to
Dental fosis ends at around 8 years old
is that that's when enamel maturation is
completed before our final permanent
teeth finish erupting after teeth are
formed Dental fluorosis can no longer
develop or worsen at one PPM one part
per million of fluoride Public Health
authorities estimated that less than 10%
of kids would develop the condition and
only in its mildest forms we've since
learned that the prevalence and severity
of fosis is much higher than predicted
according to the CDC about a third of
American children children now of some
form of dental fosis with about one in
30 experiencing a moderate or severe
case this may reflect exposure to
multiple fluoride sources not factored
into the original calculations now most
fluorosis is so mild as to be hardly
noticeable taking the form of white
streaks or splotches visible only to
dentists under the bright lights of
their exam chair but serious cases can
involve severe pitting and discoloration
and present more than just a medic
defect for example one study found that
children with severe cases are more
likely to be viewed by their peers as
less attractive less careful less clean
less happy less healthy less intelligent
less kind less reliable less social
imagine what that could do to a kid's
self-esteem given the higher than
expected rates of fosis in 2015 the US
Public Health Service reduced the
recommended fluoride concentration of
drinking water down to 0.7 parts per
million across the board and previously
levels were set at up to 1.2 PPM in
cooler areas where people tend to drink
less water this change would be
estimated to keep the percentage of
those developing fosis of aesthetic
concern down to approximately
12% in terms of other health concerns
until recently mainstream medicine's
view might have perhaps best been summed
up by the final statement in an
exhaustive report published by consumer
reports in 1978 quote the simple truth
is that there is no scientific
controversy over the safety of
fluoridation the practice is safe
economical and beneficial the survival
of this fake controversy in the consumer
Union's opinion is one of the major
triumphs of quackery over science in our
generation unquote in the last few years
though there's been growing concerns
about the adverse effects of fluoride on
brain
development which I'll
address
next there's my typical Cliffhanger
which is no problem in a webinar setting
because I just zip on right to the next
one um all right so cosmetic defects one
thing obviously um but what's this about
effects on brain development is water
floration safe or not let's find
out fluid had been found to be a
developmental neurotoxin in rats and
mice leading to learning and memory
deficits which led to an interest in
studying human populations starting in
the 1980s reports started appearing in
Chinese medical journals that found
correlations between areas naturally
containing higher fluoride levels in
water with lower intelligence among
children dental fluorosis the fluoride
induced tooth modeling is widespread in
China with more than 90 million
residents affected often in small
Pockets surrounding particular small
Springs or Mountain sources researchers
took advantage of the fact that even
adjoining neighborhoods could have
widely different fluoride exposure
setting up a kind of natural
experiment due to limited access to
Chinese journals at the time these
studies largely escaped the attention of
scientists in the west until a
metaanalysis of 16 such studies was
published in English in 2008 fluide and
children's intelligence a metaanalysis
found that children living in areas
prone to fosis had five times High rods
of developing low IQ than those living
in areas with little or no fluorosis so
here we were thinking Dental fosis was
just a cosmetic blemish but it may
instead be a visual indicator of
intellectual deficits a subsequent
metaanalysis in 2012 including about 10
more studies found that the average
intelligence gap between high and low
fluoride exposure areas was about seven
IQ points by far the largest study
involving thousands of children found
that even at fluoride levels below 1 PPM
higher fluoride levels were associated
with a large drop in the chances of
developing excellent intelligence
defined as an IQ of 130 or higher even
very mild fosis was associated with less
than half the odd of reaching such a
high
IQ by now there have been more than 50
studies showing an association between
higher fluoride exposure and lower IQ in
the latest systematic review meta
analysis 90% of the studies in the last
10 years reported the link between High
fluoride exposure and reduced
intelligence however serious caveats are
in order first the fluoride
concentrations in most of these studies
were well above fluoridation levels in
the 2012 meta analysis for example one
study clock concentrations as high as
11.5 PPM far exceeding the US Target of
0.7 parts per million as well as the
average concentration in the United
States which is around 8 PPM and in
Municipal Water and 3 PPM in wellwater
now to be fair I mean the 11 PPM in the
metaanalysis that that was an outlier I
mean the average elevated level was only
about two parts per million and most
found Associated IQ decrements below the
epa's upper limit it its maximum
contaminant level goal of 4 PPM which is
supposed to represent the level below
which there is no known or expected risk
to health some studies showed lower
intelligence with fluoride
concentrations even down at at 1 to 2
PPM with one estimate suggesting the
smallest harmful concentration
potentially shaving off a single IQ
point would be down
around3 PPM assuming you drink four cups
of water a day While others suggest it's
too early to be able to calculate a
threshold for human neurotoxicity due to
insufficient available
data the second major caveat is
confounding and nearly all the studies
to date have been performed in rural
communities in countries like China Iran
Mongolia areas within these countries
with unusually high fluoride levels may
be particularly poor and underdeveloped
since relatively rich communities may be
more likely to invest in higher quality
drinking water that filters out fluoride
if only to reduce Dental fosis High
fluoride water may also be more likely
to be contaminated with other
neurotoxins fluoride exists in water as
a negatively charged particle to
maintain electr neutrality this may pull
into the groundwater positively charge
particles such as aluminum arsenic lead
or Mercury this doesn't happen in
community water fluoridation since the
negative fluoride ions are balanced out
in the water treatment process finally
most of the older studies were
cross-sectional and ecological meaning
they looked at a snapshot in time of
group level data rather than individual
exposures over time just because a child
with low IQ lives in a high fluoride
area doesn't necessarily mean they or
their mom actually drank the water for
example
ideally we'd be able to measure
individual exposure levels and fall the
kids over time to see if those with
higher exposure really do grow up with
stunted intellects and that's exactly
what we'll cover in my next video
entitled why I changed my mind on water
fluoridation okay so growing
evidence is that this could be an issue
for fetal development but all the
studies could be rightfully criticized
for their various limitations but
then the Canadian study came out check
it
out Community water fluoridation
recently hit its 75th Anniversary touted
as a significant advancement in public
health but new research suggests the the
potential for adverse Health impacts
there's little question that
supplemental fluoride strengthens teeth
and reduces Decay but it what caused
most of the older studies were snapshot
in time studies looking only at group
level data or based on higher than
normal exposure this has since changed
with a publication of prospective
studies following individual exposure
levels from mother child pairs over time
the first few were from Mexico and
correlated higher fluoride levels in the
urine of pregnant women with future
developmental delay in their infants
they found worse cognitive performance
at age 4 and lower IQ from ages 6
through 12 but the fluoride was from
fluoridated salt or water sources where
fluoride was present naturally then this
study came out of Canada the first
prospective study using individual
exposure data dealing directly with
Community water fluoridation receiving
quote unquote optimally fluoridated
water none of the Municipal Water
fluoride levels exceeded 1.5 parts per
million and the vast majority over 90%
were under the US Target of 7 despite
drinking optimally fluoridated water the
study of more than 500 mother child
pairs found that higher fluide exposure
during pregnancy once again appeared to
translate into lower child intelligence
measured at ages 3 to 4 the American
College of Obstetrics and gynecologists
recommends pregnant women drink at least
eight cups of water a day based on the
Canadian study following this advice
with water at us Target fluoridation
levels might result in as much as a
fivepoint loss in
IQ the Canadian study was published in
the American medical journal
association's Pediatrics journal the
longest running Pediatrics journal in
the country the editor-in-chief defended
its decision to publish the study quote
as Testament to the fact that jamama
pediatric is committed to disseminating
the best science regardless of how
contentious the result may be unquote
the Canadian Agency for drugs and
Technologies and health issued a rapid
response report concluding that there is
insufficient evidence to conclusively
conclude that fluoride exposure at
Optimum levels affects neurological
development but that's not what the
Canadian study was saying the researcher
just suggested the possible need to
reduce fluoride intake during
pregnancy as the accompanying editorial
concluded based on the new data a
dispassionate and tempered discover of
fluid's potential neurotoxicity is
warranted what was the response from us
Regulators within a month of the
Canadian Studies released the national
toxicology program which is part of the
US Department of Health and Human
Services that evaluates substances for
potentially harmful human health effects
released a draft evaluation of fluoride
exposure and neurodevelopmental and
cognitive health effects and concluded
that quote based on a systematic review
of The Evidence the NT concludes that
fluide is presumed to be a cognitive
neurodevelopmental Hazard to humans
unquote so we've gone from dismissing
people who question the safety of water
fluoridation as zealots or anti-science
Fanatics to the official US national
toxicology program saying we should
presume it's
hazardous now this was just a draft
report to ensure the Integrity of its
report the ntps the National Academy is
probably our most prec prestigious
scientific institution to review it the
review raised a bunch of concerns which
was portrayed in the dental literature
as discrediting the IQ research but
that's not what the National Academy
said they explicitly said that their
misgivings don't mean that the ntp
conclusion that fluoride should be
presumed to be neurotoxic is incorrect
they just wanted some further analysis
so in 2020 they redrafted their draft
and once again came to the same
conclusion presuming it's a cognitive
neurodevelopmental Hazard based on the
extent consistency and robustness of the
IQ Data the national Academy's then
re-reviewed their redrafted draft
concluding it's much improved but urged
the ntp to further improve the clarity
of the document and we await the final
ntp
report okay so that really does change
everything now in the book that's where
the section
uh but I was so interested to see how
the medical and dental professions would
react to this like total 180 among
Regulators from presumptively safe to
presumptively dangerous so bonus video
um before I take questions how did the
medical profession respond to the
changing fluide science let's find
out
the national toxicology program is part
of the Public Health Service in
partnership with the CDC FDA and NIH
dedicated to the analysis of Agents of
concern to identify any toxic effects
how did the medical community respond to
the draft conclusions their recent
systematic review that concluded that
floride is to be presumed to be a
cognitive neurodevelopmental Hazard to
humans based on studies showing lower IQ
scores among kids with higher fluoride
exposure what do you do when current
research contradicts public practices
when new evidence doesn't conform with
existing beliefs well health authorities
have continued to conclude that fluoride
is unequivocally safe despite the new
studies in recent years linking fluide
exposure and pregnancy with adverse
effects on fetal brain development there
are still papers on how to sell
fluoridation of the water supply
targeting social media and the personto
person spread of fluoride
misinformation search engines are to be
encouraged at the very least to flag
search engine results that point to
water fluoridation Health misinformation
suggesting adverse effects in promoting
support for Community water fluoridation
maybe we don't even want to Proclaim its
safety for fear of raising questions
about risks I mean if you're saying it's
safe then that begs a question well is
it not safe maybe we shouldn't even talk
about whether it's safe the tendency to
ignore new evidence that does not
conform to widespread beliefs maybe
impeding our response to early warnings
about fluide as a potential
developmental neurotoxin but some are
just so fixed in their views on
fluoridation that they won't reassess
their stance no matter what the latest
research might show
ironically it was the anti fluoridation
ISS who were accused of their
anti-scientific attitudes but now it's
the pro- fluoridation is one of the most
fastel pro- fluoridation arguments I ran
across is the suggestion that fluoride
can't be hurting IQs because over the
last half century of fluoridation IQ
scores have been going up rather than
down the jawdropping irony is that a
substantial part of that rise may have
been due to the removal of another
neurotoxic element lead it's worth
remembering that the science surrounding
the neurodevelopmental hazard of
low-level lead exposure was also
bitterly contested using the same kind
of arguments we see today in the
fluoridation debate a few short years
before leaded gas was effectively banned
in the United States a metaanalysis of
lead exposure in child IQ only found 24
human studies all cross-sectional with a
typical Associated loss of intelligence
about four IQ points the current data
suggests a similar IQ loss from fluoride
from an even stronger body of evidence a
spokesperson for the American Dental
Association responded to the new data
pointing out that some cities that have
ended water fluoridation saw an increase
in cavities
okay but that's kind of a strange
response to data suggesting the
potential for permanent brain damage in
children I mean I I know they're the
Dental Association but how could they so
easily ignore the serious red flags of
potential neurotoxicity for cavity
reduction this is not to say tooth decay
isn't a serious health issue but there
are ways to get the cavity preventing
benefits of fluoride without the risks
since the primary benefits arise from
topical contact with our enamel but the
primary risk arise from systemic
absorption we can follow Europe's
example and safely reap the rewards
using fluoride toothpaste and
mouthwashes in Europe 98% of the
population drink unfluoridated water uh
several countries including France
Germany the Netherlands Denmark Sweden
banned fluoridation decades ago in favor
of fluoride toothpaste as more than 10
years ago the official scientific
committee on health risk of the European
Union concluded that topical application
fluoride is most effective in preventing
tooth decay and there appears to be no
obvious advantage in favor of
fluoridating the water
supply okay so Best of Both Worlds can
be gained by topical application of
fluoride so I continue to use and
Advocate the fluoride tooth base but
pregnant breastfeeding women may want to
consider non fluoridated water sources
to reduce the apparent risk to the
developing
brain all right Q&A time I'm sure
there's lots of Juicy questions out
there let me just give our nutrition
fact Stamp five minutes to compile the
most commonly asked questions and then I
will be right
back okay we have lots of Juicy
wonderful questions let's do this number
one on the list is are these potential
harms only relevant for children or do
adults need to be careful with fluoride
too such as
nonchildbearing age adults and the
answer is we don't know um all we um in
fact there's I think there's only been
two adult studies ever um and so all we
know is that appears to be so when I say
uh develop neural a neurodevelopmental
hazard we're talking about as as it
sounds like you understand we're talking
about the formation of brains in utero
and probably during breastfeeding as
well um and so once you already have
your brain is fluoride toxic the
question the answer is we just don't
know I mean there's just not um uh just
not enough data out there um I mean I
can certainly understand people are like
you know well look you know lead's bad
you know lead's bad for baby brains
lead's bad for adult brains you know
fluoride might be bad for baby's brains
or maybe bad for adult brains too that's
possible um but we just uh we don't have
good data um to support that it would
all be speculation at this point now you
think though maybe we should actually
fund some studies what do you think
anyway all right are carbon filters or
other other water filtration systems for
that matter capable of removing um or
reducing fluoride from drinking water
from tap was the best source of water or
filter without fluorid bottle water the
best source of spring water safe
alternative to floridated tap water um
so yeah most filtration systems are not
going to get rid of
fluide um although um it's possible that
reverse osmosis um systems will um and
you know the bottled water Spring Water
depends on the source right remember
fluoride is a natural constituent of
Water Supplies around the world um and
so you know wellwater has has you know
three you know parts per million on
average in the United States some's
higher some's lower um that's not
floridated that's just seeping uh
fluoride from uh the element from the
Earth's crust into the water um table so
uh the bottle water um may not have
intentionally added fluoride in it but
it might naturally um have fluoride in
it same thing with spring water um oh
turn off screen share oh oh I'm sorry ah
I'm
sorry um the next question was turn off
screen share so we can see you on the
full screen H okay there we go
good okay uh what about uh what about
chlorine what about oh what about
chlorine in water especially excessive
amounts use for old pipes is the floral
plus chloro combo especially bad well
I've got a video on at least that I'm
going to to uh copy paste it check this
out we have this new fancy shortener c.
NF Slater so now you so you don't even
have to memorize it or click on it um
se. nfw waterer um is the video where I
talk about chlorination byproducts um
and the increased risk of bladder cancer
um so how much bladder cancer and why
it's But the irony is we're trying to
make the water safer from a bacteria
standpoint but can actually make it um
less safe from a kind of chemical safety
standpoint uh but there's a way to get
clean water without use without using
chlorine chlorine but it is expensive
anyway okay so it's fascinating video so
check it out I don't talk about fluoride
there but I do talk about the
chlorination byproducts which are indeed
a concern um and uh and I talk about how
regular carbon filters activate uh
charcoal filters like pure and brda and
refrigerator filters and stuff can
actually reduce some of those floration
byproducts okay uh next up type of
fluoride utilized in toothpaste is
different than the type utilized in
drinking water so is there a difference
and side effects um well it's probably
the fluoride so we think it's the
fluoride not the like so if it's sodium
fluoride we don't think it's the sodium
that's doing we think it's the fluoride
so fluoride um so regardless of what
kind of flu what kind of like fluoride
salt is used um when you stick in water
it should just ionize into fluoride um
and uh and uh cause whatever things that
causes so I would not I would assume it
would be the same although I didn't run
across any um studies either way does
fluide negatively afflect bones does it
make bones brittle that's what I was
talking about skeletal fluorosis I think
it was the second video where I talked
about fluorosis which is you know
usually just that modeling of the teeth
but at high levels um you can get
skeletal fosis and I actually talk about
um um someone who drank too much tea
like I don't know 20 bags of
lipin you know uh iced tea a day um and
had got so much fluoride that you
actually had uh had skeletal
fosis um and so at really high levels
yes I it can affect your bones okay next
question does fluide build up cumin to
live in our body to create toxicity how
long does it take for added fluoride to
flush out of our body system um well so
fluoride can be uh so fluoride can just
flow right through US unless it becomes
incorporated into bone or in case of
your teeth the enamal um and so uh but
like the reason you don't have to worry
about uh Dental fluorosis after the
permanent teeth come in is because it's
only incorporating that fluid when the
teeth are being formed when the teeth
areed form then no longer you could have
as high fluoride as you want you're not
going to um uh affect that kind of
modeling but your bones are being
remodeled all the time you're making
bones breaking down bone all the time um
and it can incorporate some of the
fluoride and so in that way you can kind
of build some up a lead does the same
thing um in fact I have a whole series
of videos on lead talking about how um
one of the reasons we don't want
breastfeeding women to be losing weight
um is
because uh not only all all these toxic
pollutant build up in their body fat
which come roaring out into their
bloodstream and end up in their breast
milk but also um as they're uh um we're
going to lose bone mass and loss of bone
mass will release lead that'll get into
the the breast milk too okay a fluoride
free toothpaste contains titanium
dioxide I understand it's not a safe
ingredient any other are there any
ingredients in fluoride free toothpaste
that we should avoid um I'm sure not all
fluoride free toothpaste contain T
titanium dioxide it's just used to make
things look white and I know there's
lots of to toothpaste that don't go out
of their B to make you know things look
bright um uh but titanium dioxide should
only be a problem if you
actually uh swallow it um so for example
you know use topically um it's one of
the one of the two safe sunscreens
because it doesn't get absorbed through
the skin um and so as long as you're not
drinking it or eating it shouldn't be a
problem um and but I do have a video
about
titanium um dioxide in terms of as a
food out it to make like candy white and
things um and uh so you can check that
out on nutritionfacts.org oh in terms of
other ingredients um
SLS wasn't that um I do have uh video
talking about uh sodium Laural
sulfate oh okay here
let's um well here I'll just share the
regular URL um so sodium lural sulfate
sulfate I talk about how it's kind of a
detergent that um can hurt your gums and
then I talk about well there's this all
this not in the
sls3 toothpaste there's another compound
that's used that's gives you the same
problems and so you ideally would have a
toothpaste with that eye there good luck
finding that okay um is zyol okay in
toothpaste yes um just don't let your
dog eat it is orthol safe and better
than fluoride in toothpaste well orthol
is safe and better than Xylitol I
actually just did a video about that
recently um but the
arrol um does uh interfere with the
growth of those bad bacteria um and so
can decrease risk of cavities um but is
not considered a substitute for fluoride
and what about hydroxy appetite not
something I looked
into do children need fluoride
toothpaste and so starting on what age
are kids safe from fluoride induced
neurotoxicity after a certain age the
reason why you know there's all these
instructions how you want to have a psz
amount of toothpaste and be very careful
and you know monitor supervise kids when
they brushes because we don't want them
swallowing um too much fluoride and so
um all those
caveats uh along with all those caveats
you know as long as they're spitting it
out um we don't have to worry about
their
brains um any insight on tooth mineral
remineralization powders coning ground
cloves and calcium carbonate as Dental
alternative fluide treatments for cavity
prevention that sounds
fishy um I yeah never heard of such a
thing sounds fishy but uh didn't run
across any uh any science either way
calwell Lon
D has been saying that floridated Water
and toothpaste destroy those wonderful
bacteria on their tongue that convert
nitrates to nitrides I could not find
such evidence um if that were true that
would be a significant um strike against
it but I could not find um evidence that
it hurts your those good bugs and we can
help those good bugs with tooth uh not
tooth cleaning tongue cleaning tongue
scraping have a video about that okay
are there potential neurodevelopmental
effects Beyond reduced IQ other
neurological conditions you know that's
a good question one would assume so I
mean so IQ is kind of used as a kind of
General cognitive indicator um but you
know so if it hurts IQ it's hurting all
sorts of aspects of cognition um but
that's the only one that's really been
kind of
validated um and so so uh so we really
don't know but I would not be surprised
I mean something's bad for the brain
it's bad for the brain um any thoughts
on glass
isomer restorative material that
releases fluoride slowly as a filling
huh what's the safest type of filling
well so I am certainly no expert in this
area in fact I only know of two kinds of
fillings composite fillings and the you
know amalgam or Mercury fillings um and
so I would um the downside the amalg
fillings is mercury obviously and the
downside of the composite fillings are
BPA that platic compound I'd rather have
BPA in my system than mercury in my
system but maybe there's some glass ICM
or one that I've never heard
about I I do not know but that sounds
like a good video actually um although
I've never been offered that in a
dentist so if you can't really get it I
don't know what the point is but maybe
that's the wave of the future are those
who eat a lot of fruit at higher risk
for tooth decay no but they are at
higher risk of
uh of of hurting their
enamel um which is that extra hard layer
um on the outside of your teeth um it
can erode away you can get enamel
erosion if you eat sour foods and
beverages
without rinse your mouth out with water
afterwards that's the critical piece you
eat all the fruit you want all the
sourness you want drink that hibiscus
tea chew on Raw crime berries whatever
you want
stuck on a lemon
but got to rinse your mouth out with
water to get those acids off your
teeth um and critically you don't want
to be
brushing um afterwards because you're
tooth are in a softened State and then
you're GNA be brushing off your enamel
ah so rinse with water wait at least an
hour um afterwards before you brush your
teeth all right oh this is after eating
something sour or acidic same thing like
apple cided vinegar a diluted appid of
vinegar you want to rinse your mouth out
with water
afterwards okay how crucial is it to get
oral care products that are certified by
the Ada the American Dental Association
now I
assume they I don't know what their
criteria are I'm assure I assume they
don't um certify anything any like
toothpaste if it doesn't have fluoride
in it but I don't know if they have any
other criteria than that um what do I
suggest for drinking water while
traveling
um so again um what we know is the
concern during pregnancy what if you're
pregnant and drinking water while
traveling um
uh I unless well I mean if you're
traveling a 100% of the time then
there's really not much you can do
presumably to have control over your
water supply since you can't even get
water onto an airplane right it's not
like you could bring water with you and
I don't think there's like
some Pock ET filtration system so I mean
I just wouldn't worry about it when
you're traveling because PE people
typically travel very a very small
percentage of the time uh but yeah if
you were on the road forever I do not
know what you would just probably be
exposed to a lot of fluid unless you
were traveling anywhere else in the
world where basically they don't uh
fluoridate their water what about green
tea I understand most teas contain High
fluoride concentration then uh a higher
fluide concentration of fluoridated
water um that's a well I mean that's why
I recommend green teas
mouthwash um because partially because
of its fluoride content partially
because it decreases the um growth of
cavity producing bacteria um but you can
overdo it um and so you know I have a
video talking about how much tea is too
much from a lead standpoint depending on
whether you buy it from China or Japan
whether it's black or green have a video
about that so I'd have to see if those
kind of the highest levels of tea
consumption you would run into
floration uh you know for for people
that basically drink tea instead of
water um uh
so uh so that's a good question that's a
good question um but uh and I bet I I
bet in my scill to fosis Te video I talk
about how much is actually in Te so you
can kind of
run the numbers
yourself okay what are our
thoughts um what are your thoughts that
some dentist recommend not to use
toothpaste at all because toothpaste is
abrasive to teeth well I assume the
abrasiveness of toothpaste is on
purpose um to try to get uh to try to
get that
plaque um off um uh but the most
important thing you can do to prevent
cavities is
not eat added sugar right there's if you
look at the
skulls of people that lived a million
years ago guess what and they had no
toothbrushes at all no toothpaste guess
what basically no cavities how is that
even possible the floss wasn't invented
well guess what wasn't invented candy
bars weren't invented right um basically
um cavities have one and only cause
and that is added sugars um and you can
prove this for all sorts of ways you
know there was like when when we had uh
um you know the were wartime
deprivations when all of a sudden people
couldn't get sugar cavity uh levels
plummet um um but even like down like
one to three% of calories from sugar you
can still make cavities so it's really
cutting out
sugary um Foods
period um but that's good for all sorts
of reasons
okay what about coconut oil turmeric or
baking soda instead of
toothpaste I think if you use turmeric
your teeth would turn
yellow don't quote me but it's pretty
staining
stuff um so if you wanted yellow teeth
that might do it um but I don't other
than that I don't know uh uh I I don't
know the toothpaste composition
ingredients um or there hasn't been I
haven't run across science either way
how would cutting down on flid ingestion
by switching water sources compared to
the benefit of cleaning our produce of
oh pesticides assuming there is some
issue at all is one more important than
the other oh that's an interesting
question Okay C okay so the benefits of
cutting the known or presumed benefits
of cutting down fluid ingestion is um so
that our fetuses in our
bodies grow up to have smarter
brains um and the concern about uh
pesticides um has to do with cancer
risk um so it's kind of a totally
different thing and then that's cancer
risk kind for everybody not just for
pregnant people
um and cleaning our produce so I have a
video talking about how much you can
change pesticide levels on produce
through various methods of cleaning them
he doesn't usually wash them all off it
just drops them a little bit but even if
you didn't wash them at
all the benefit from eating more fruits
and vegetables vastly outweighs um any
potential risks from uh pesticide
exposure even if all you had were the
most contaminated um conventional
produce um a tremendous benefit in Risk
versus uh benefit versus a tiny bump in
risk and so uh concerns about pesticides
should not prevent us from stuffing our
faces with as many fruits and vegetables
as
possible um another question
recommendations for testing fluoride in
the home I am sure there's an industry
out there
that has has has has come up where you
can send off a water sample I know you
can do it for well so I this is the
first time I've living with I'm living
with well water and I know we sent it
off for looking at like coli levels and
stuff so presumably you can get sent for
fluoride there may even be like a meter
you can stick into your water that's not
something I looked into apologize about
that all right we are almost closed down
let me just tell you about the new
webinar is coming up um all sorts of
Juicy topics I had to cut from the book
um like sunscreen safety I gave people a
little preview um Al collagen
supplements next webinar is on
osteoporosis on May 12th tons of new
stuff I learned about
osteoporosis um so stay tuned and don't
want to jinx it we may actually be able
to offer CM continu medical education uh
credits for health professionals fingers
crossed we're working on it um so just
make sure you're signed up to the
nutritionfacts.org email newsletter to
uh for all the future details thanks
everybody uh for joining me for this uh
interesting topic stay safe be kind and
eat your vegetables
it's